okay hi everyone uh welcome to magnets um so the
similar format is as usual 25 minutes presentation
during which i recommend you keep your microphone
mutes um and then there's gonna be time for
questions and answers uh any question is welcome
you can text you can put use the chat box if you
want and and after uh this part is going to be
a part that is not recorded that you can stay
for an informal catch up it would be nice so for
today i'm very excited we have uh marco maffione
presenting uh uh the um the presentational
title tilt correction versus net rotation
poly magnetic analysis um so thanks marco
thank you very much for accepting orientation
and the floors is yours now okay so let me share
okay so let me share my screen and
can you all see this
yeah yeah okay yes thank you thank you thank
you for the invitation anita and craig um
so what i want to talk about today is about a very
broadly uh known and applied method in magnetic
analysis which is the tilt correction what i
will talk about will be the about the limitation
of this method and how we can overcome uh problems
about this method with another approach which is
known as net tectonic rotation i will also talk
about the limitation of the net tectonic rotation
analysis uh so we'll conclude this uh talk
by showing you some data some applications
of the netatonic rotation that we did in
the past so um to start i first of all
want to make some acknowledgments uh because um
i'm not the first let's say person to use this one
i'm actually one of the last and all i know about
this method is coming from tony morris uh plymouth
uh which i've collaborated with since 2010 and so
he told me everything about this this method so
basically he's my my mentor in this in this topic
he published several papers applying these methods
in in cyprus uh intruder sophia line uh since
1990 then 1998 he applied the method to other
officialites in syria and then we ended up
writing a paper together in cyprus in 2016.
so what we can say about the tilt correction
is that the tilt correction approach
it's uh it's mainly based on the assumption
that deformation can be decomposed into two
components of rotation one is a tilt and
the other one is a vertical axis rotation
that's a big assumption and you will see how
this can actually produce some bias in the
interpretation so as a general point of view what
we typically do in paleomagnetic analysis when we
apply the analysis to deformation analysis and
restoration what we do we measure the remnants
in a specific rock which could be a sediment or
it could be volcanic layer and what we measure is
called the in-situ magnetization and then because
this unit is not um as in the original position
but it's been affected by local deformation
which here is observed as a tilt what we
typically do we remove the tilt by performing a
strike parallel rotation by doing so we correct
this in situ by the magnetic direction and we
obtain a new magnetic direction that we call
the tilt corrected direction and then what we
do we compare once this is the tilt corrected
in other words correspond to the direction of
the magnetic field when the rock was horizontal
uh we then compared that to a reference direction
which is typically a direction from a tectonic
plate where the rocks has been sampled from
and we infer the vertical axis rotation
it's a very simple approach everybody used
it and including me and other people so it's
nothing wrong with this but i'll show you
the limitations of this method in a second
the limitations have actually been
already identified in the early 80s by
mcdonald who published this paper talking about
the tilt correction and he actually recognized
that there are some miscalculations that you
you may introduce by when you have some specific
let's say tectonic configurations or or tectonic
um let's say process going on uh in fact what he
says is that you can actually ended up recording
not the true tectonic rotation by the apparent
so in other words it's not the real one and when
we have this it's essentially in two situations
the first one is when the rotation are not
parallel to the strike which is something
one of the main assumption of the tilt correction
and the tilt correction method um we can actually
in fact have some some weird rotation not
weird but some let's say uncommon rotation axis
or maybe they are common who knows that are not
horizontal but they are inclined so in this case
basically what you calculate you will end up
calculating an apparent tectonic rotation the
second condition to introduce this bias is
when you have multiple phases of rotations
so imagine some situation like this when you have
like a first bending and then a faulting so when
you have multiple phases of rotation you also
end up calculating an apparent tectonic rotation
when you apply a tilt correction so um this is for
sediments so horizon originally horizontal layers
the situation is even more dramatic when we apply
the tail correction in dykes and i'm talking about
shitty dykes because it's what i've been
working on so far so originally vertical dykes
if you apply a teal correction on diets you
are 100 sure you are going to introduce error
again what we do or what people have been
doing in dykes is taking dyke performing a
dike parallel rotation to restore it to vertical
and then from the till corrected direction here
again you compare it to a reference direction
and you calculate the vertical axis rotation
now the main problem with dikes is that you cannot
resolve any components of rotations that are
perpendicular to the dike in fact if you look
at this image if you rotate the spike which is
originally vertical by 40 degrees by 90 degrees by
450 degrees nothing will change to the strike or
so the only way here to realize that some rotation
occurred is by looking at the remnants direction
so in dikes the situation as i said is quite
complex it's quite critical when we apply till
correction and you cannot resolve those dike
normal components of rotation in other words
because a dike parallel rotation it's pretty
much a big coincidence so we imply that every
rotation it's most of the time not parallel to the
strike then we can conclude that applying this to
dike can always or 99.9 of the time introduce an
error okay so how do we uh overcome this problem
the alternative method that have been introduced
by alerton and vine in in 1987 it's called
the net tectonic rotation now the net tectonic
rotation um is essentially calculates a single
rotation around an inclined axis that can restore
the structure to the original position which is
what the kill correction approach does but on top
of this the net tectonic rotation also wants to
restore the in-situ magnetization to the reference
magnetization now the reference magnetization
is the original direction the magnetic field
recorded by the rock when the rock was already
was still in situ so before any deformation so in
other words in the tilt correction we only look
at this portion so we take the structure back
to the original position and we calculate the
tilt corrected magnetization which is not here in
this approach so if we look at dikes for example
when you take this strike in the original position
um the stack is affected by some deformation
you can see here the remnants in blue and we also
uh highlighted the dyke uh to this uh the pole to
this dike in red what the netatonic rotation
analysis does is calculate a inclined axis
rotation that can restore
simultaneously the type to vertical
so in other words this pole will correspond
to that pole so bring it back to horizontal
but also the remnants back to the original
remnants what we called the reference direction
so it's a double correction so you bypass
the till correction uh the till corrected
direction that you obtain in the tilt correction
approach now this net tectonic rotation analysis
is based on several assumptions uh the first one
is that you can identify that reference direction
and that could be the direction expected
from a specific plate where you collected
the data from or it could be any other direction
could be the geographic direction so the north
you just want to see what was the
deformation of your rock from north and so on
the second assumption is that as in any other kind
of paleomagnetic analysis you want your remnants
to be pre-deformation and possibly primary the
third assumption is that you want to restore your
structures back to the original position so
we assume strata like sedimentary beds to be
originally horizontal and dikes not all dikes but
maybe dikes in ortholytic complex shaded diets
back to vertical and the last one and probably
most important and you will see in a moment
why is that there is no internal strain in your
rock so the rock shouldn't be deformed internally
now let's see what the netatonic rotation analysis
can calculate for us um so these are the three
kind of input data that we have at the beginning
of our analysis so we we have measured the in-situ
magnetization of our rock we have measured the
structure in this particular example is based
on dikes that were originally vertical so this
would be the pole to die and that is our reference
magnetization so because we want to restore so
the net atomic rotation analysis restores the
in situ magnetization to the initial magnetization
which is our reference but also the structure back
to the original position we can obtain multiple
solutions from this analysis the first solution
is the initial structure the initial orientation
of in this case of the dyke so what you have at
the beginning is that your the angle between
the measured magnetization and your structure
in this case will be the pole to the dyke
that this distance measured as an angle
angled beta that angle will not change during all
deformations that this rock can ever experience
so that angle will stay the same so everything uh
incision magnetization and pole to die will rotate
two three four so many times but that angle will
not change so what we know is that originally
the in-situ magnetization was coincident with the
reference magnetization so before deformation that
was our original magnetization because the beta
angle will stay the same then we can infer two
conditions where our dike is vertical which
is because this is the pole to the dike
these two are the only two conditions that
will restore the dike back to vertical
okay so from this we calculate the
strike the initial strike of the dikes
so the first solution of the net atomic rotation
is therefore in case of dikes will allow you to
calculate the initial orientation of the dikes and
you will see that you have two solutions so you
need to select the most geologically meaningful
based perhaps on other geological evidence
the second types or the other kind of solutions
that we can obtain with the net tectonic rotation
is the rotation pose now this uh as an image
looks pretty complex but it's actually not
and i'll go i will drive you through each step
of how we calculate the rotation axis here so the
three input vectors are this one highlighted this
is the the remnants the in-situ remnants this is
the dike pole and that is the reference direction
so as i mentioned before the lantatonic rotation
analysis performed simultaneously two rotations
the first one brings the in-situ remnants
to the reference direction which is basically
what the original direction was before deformation
and at the same time restore the structure back to
its original position so for a dike like in this
case you want the dyke to be back to vertical and
because we have two possible orientation of the
dyke could be either that rotation or the other
rotation these two points are you can see the beta
circle that will be the two initial dike
orientation okay so to perform the first rotation
we need the rotation axis that is contained within
the bisectoric plane between the two vectors
okay so we have two vectors how to
rotate this vector away from this one
is through a rotation pole that lies within
the bisectoric plane between the two vectors
which is this great circle here okay so that
satisfies the first rotation we have infinite
solutions of rotation poles here along this
great circle because we have to satisfy
also simultaneously another rotation which is
bringing back rock to in its its original position
to do that again we need another rotation axis
which brings this pole either there or there
and again the rotation pole that brings this
pole to that direction is along the bisectoric
plane which is this red line so also here
you have infinite solutions of the rotation
pole that can perform that rotation but because we
need for the netatonic rotation analysis that two
these two rotations are simultaneous there
is only one solution that satisfies both
conditions which is given by the intersection
between this two great circle which is the red
the yellow star here okay so that would be the
rotation axis that can perform uh this correction
so bring back the initial the incident remnants
to the reference but also the structure back to
initial to initial position you will see that you
have also another solution here and that's because
we have two possible initial dike orientation
so you will have another great circle bisector
between this the dipole and the other alternative
initial dike orientation so you end up with two
rotation axis orientation and from
this you can also calculate the amount
and sense of rotation that can perform this um
that brings this vector away from the reference
so this this method is has been written by
by tony a while ago on a dos program and and
i've worked on that previously but then recently
have been implemented in a in an online software
uh developed by the group in utrecht uh
led by darwin van isbergen which is called
paleomagnetism.org and in this online
software that can perform a number of
standard paleomagnetic analysis you also find the
net tectonic rotation protocol all right so this
is pretty much what i wanted to tell you about
the method um what i i will spend now the rest of
another 5-10 minutes talking about the application
and bringing you an example of how we applied the
net tectonic rotation analysis to understand the
evolution of the true dose of your light in cyprus
so the true disophelite in cyprus is a very
unique light because it's well preserved but also
it because it can serve it a fossil spreading
axis which is the solia robin here in the middle
of the island of the theophilite and also a
fossil transform fault which is the southern
trudeau's trans uh transform fault zone very
long name this black line is the transformer
so what has been observed um in the past is that
the dyke orientation which is this pink unit here
which should be parallel to the spreading axis
which is the uh indicated here by the solar graven
so the dyke when they approach the transform
they bend uh to get more almost parallel to
this transform fold and this has been studied by
several people and they have realized that indeed
the band the trend of the dykes that looks more
east-west indeed is affected by strong clockwise
rotations so that helped to understand the
kinematics of this transform fold and we realized
that clockwise rotations are typically associated
with a dextro uh strike slip fault or in this case
as a transform and therefore we developed a model
about this ophelite where um the spreading reach
is located to the to the left the the solia grab
and spreading reach and we need therefore another
segment of the reach located here to the west of
the aracapa forest so many years a few years ago
with tony actually we we performed some additional
sampling in the western part of the shitty dykes
complex of cyprus and what we realized by
simple structural analysis is that the dikes
moving away along this transect moving to the
north they get bent they they actually rotate
uh getting more into parallel to an east-west
direction rather than a north-south direction you
can see here that we over this region we observed
kind of two clusters of directions of the dykes
we then performed a classic perimagnetic analysis
we demagnetized our rocks with af the mag and
this is the in-situ remnants that we calculated
from those dikes and you can see that all of them
are different from the tmv which is the trudus
magnetization vector so the expected direction
so all those types have been
rotated from their initial position
so we applied a netatonic rotation analysis
because again you cannot apply a simple tilt
correction analysis to dykes uh we applied
net telephonic rotation on all of these sides
and we calculated the initial dike orientation
before deformation and the rotation axis for
each one of these sides the summary of all this
analysis is in this figure and i've divided here
the results from the northern domain which is the
one that shows more east-west dikes in situ from
the southern domain which is more close to the
the expected north-south directions of the dykes
so as i said before the nittatonic rotation
analysis can provide the initial dike orientation
which is here represented by this rose diagram and
you can see that despite in situ the dikes are in
the south and north domain of the standard area
they show significantly significantly different
in situ directions they initially had a pretty
much consistent uh trend when they actually were
in place in the oceanic crust then the second type
of solutions of the net tectonic rotation analysis
is the rotation axis which we we modeled here we
showed the density distribution of the rotation
axis and again what you see here is that those
types have been affected by some kind of shallow
shallowly plunging rotation axis trending slightly
to the northwest then the interesting part of the
analysis is the amount of rotation so all of
the sides have been rotated clockwise from the
original position but you can see that this is
the histogram as a frequency distribution of the
rotations and you can see that the north domain
has rotation that are nearly double the rotations
that we observe in the southern domain and this
is a pretty unique resource that we could not
have obtained with a simple tail correction
approach where only the net tectonic rotation can
allow you to to get those kind of data so in other
words to to summarize those results we observed
this is the studied area in cyprus and what
we saw was that we observed an increasing
magnitude of rotations more clockwise moving to
the north so what we interpret this kind of trend
was uh was something similar to what you
see in the in the east in the in nearby
the southern trudeau's transform and in fact here
as soon as you approach the fault the rotations
they are all clockwise because the kinematics of
this transform is textural and because we observe
a similar pattern here what we interpret was
that we must have or we we should have another
transform fault very close to the edge of
the ovulite so unfortunately we cannot test
this with field evidence because it must be
here uh just outside the of your light but
because the rotations here are so strong we
expect that this what we call the northern
trudus transform fault zone must have been very
very close to this location here and again because
the rotations are clockwise we need a textural
kinematics here therefore we need another
reach segment to be located here in the
west so this all together create a nice
very consistent um dextral kind of
step down of the spreading reach uh
of that created this this ovulate in the back
in cretaceous so to place this result into
the in situ context at the time the ovulate
was created and 93 million years ago um we
can see that basically the ophelite was pretty
much a a complete rich segment and perhaps the
transforms here this is the subduction zone of the
neo-tethys ocean that was going on at that time
uh so the isolation of the star of this
ophelite must have been therefore um
hided or or supported by the the fractures
uh let's say the discontinuities of the
transform faults that are in this in this
system all right so i want to just conclude
um with showing you some pro and cons of each
one of the two methods so the till correction and
the net tonic rotation now in terms of benefit of
pros the tip correction can provide paleo latitude
which can be sometimes very useful for specific
studies so we really want to know the latitude of
rock and you only can obtain that if you calculate
the till correct direction of magnetization
which cannot be obtained by the net atomic
rotation analysis the other pro of the tilt
correction is that it's quite reliable when we
deal with simple structures so structures that
either experience the simple tilt by just very
normal kind of geological structures like normal
falls reverse faults and maybe with just one
phase of deformation the benefit of applying
the net tectonic rotation analysis is that it's
the only method necessary for for dikes especially
sheeted dykes that were originally vertical okay
so if you're dealing with that you need to apply
net tonight rotation analysis and the other
pro is that the application can be necessary
in very complexly deformed structures so when
you have multiple phases of deformation then
the the negative side of the till corrections
is that we calculate um the apparent rotation
in case the the deformation is very complex
so you don't calculate the true rotation
which means that you introduce a number
of errors in your calculations and
on the other side the negative side of the
metatonic rotation is that you cannot obtain
a paleo altitude as you may need in several in
several studies the other negative side of the
tonic rotation is that there are some limitations
due to some technicality of the method and
because of time constraint i cannot discuss about
this but there has been a paper published by
titus and davis last year that talk about all
these potential limitations of the net atomic
rotations um and yeah with this one i think i've
i've concluded so thank you for your attention
thank you very much marco thank you
let's give marco a big round of applause
thank you video presentation thanks um now
there is time for questions should anybody
hi i have a question um so it seemed to
me when i was working on dykes and trottos
you have a package of a dyke swarm like
in one outcrop you have a bunch of dikes
they're not sheeted dikes they're just a bunch
of dikes most of them are not sheeted and the
average uh was probably vertical but but
there's quite a bit of um you know 10 20 degrees
for any individual dike so do you take how
do you approach that do you take the average
and then call that used to be vertical yes yeah so
it's a good question you're totally right indeed
when you go in the field you see dykes can swing
quite brutally from you know from one another they
do what they want in the example they go well
wherever they find the space and indeed uh my
approach which is pretty much what uh should be
uh done in the field is to measure multiple dikes
from one location uh so i typically measured um
about ten dikes and then calculated an error uh
take calculated an average and then an error of
that direction and in fact something i didn't
mention is that you can go even further with
the analysis you can do a modeling of the error
yeah you can model the error around the three
input vectors so this the integer remnant has
an error which is the alpha 95 then the dike
direction has an error because of this measurement
of different dikes in one station and then the
remnants direction also has an error which is the
alpha 95 of the remnants so indeed that measuring
multiple dikes is actually essential if you want
to do this properly and in theory it should
give the vertical direction when you average
out let's say 10 likes we may be off of some
degrees who knows but that's the best we can do
okay thank you yeah in fact actually the the
paper of uh titus and davis the one i mentioned
at the end uh the the limitations are in fact
uh basically introduced when the dikes are
not perfectly vertical right and they said they
calculated exactly how much error you introduce
for each degree away from the
verticality and but yeah right okay
thank you uh any other question
tony
yeah it's just a corollary of that really
following on from lisa's um question and
marco's answer is that um if you want to apply
this to like discrete dikes in another setting
then you've got to be really really careful
because you know we you can be pretty sure
that the average orientation of a whole
suite of sheeted dikes is originally
vertical because of the tectonic scenario in
which those dikes form but if you're sampling
you know individual dikes that are cutting through
sedimentary layers for instance or whatever
um then they do go wherever they want to go you
know they're responding to the local stress field
and and that might not be originally vertical
yeah so in that case in those cases neither
the till correction and nor the the net atomic
rotation analysis are reliable enough for saying
for calculating the rotation of those dikes so
it may be better to stay away from those dikes
maybe i was wondering sorry to jump in uh if you
can combine actually field evidence for instance
if you have a die can you that's including through
sedimentary layers you have some tilting observing
sedimentary layers so you can kind of tilt
everything back in a way i don't know if you
need that replication for that no yeah i mean if
you have the the main problem with dykes is that
you don't have the paleo horizontal and if you do
have a pale horizontal constraint which can come
from sediments on top and between knows what
the situation is then yes you can actually
use that and basically you can either apply the
net tectonic rotation uh using the horizontal
so just bringing back those layers to horizontal
which i haven't discussed i always made examples
about dykes but you can apply the net tectonic
rotation analysis also to horizontal layers and
and then yeah so you can either
do one or the other in those those
circumstances sure thanks i i would i would
think that you can use kind of a multiple kind
of restoring back if the deformation is assumed
to be kind of coheival in a way right yeah
yeah absolutely okay thank you um any other
question greg hi marco um so you you use the
sort of differential rotation between the
the northern domain and the southern domain
to infer the presence of a transformed fault in
the north and but you see that i mean there's no
other physical evidence there because it's it's
it's no longer part of the of you like are there
any is there anything else that you can look at
to to to confirm um that there was a transform
fault in in the north of the ophelia we could move
to the west sorry to the east and looking to the
look into the the pillows because you as soon
as you stay to the west of the soliagraven
you if our interpretation is true you should
expect some strong rotation in the upper part of
the if you like but also because the office has a
kind of a the orientation is it's not suitable so
if i show again the map basically if you move from
the highest point where we saw this high rotation
in dikes you move to the east you probably get
into this sedimentary cover above the ufo light
but anyway that that could be a way to test that
just looking a little bit more to the east and
see whether you see the consistent rotations
otherwise i'm not sure how other what other um
evidence we can claim because indeed the ovulation
just ends there so the other part knows of that
potential transform has never been in
place so it's a it's an idea it's a model
maybe true maybe not that's the
that's what the data are suggesting
thank you lisa yeah so um i was
just thinking there must be we have
hundreds and hundreds of dikes that we drilled
and have the data for um uh and there have been so
many studies there must be thousands and thousands
of dikes that have been drilled and and measured
and all this um stuff and i was just wondering
wouldn't it be nice to compile all those data
together in some consistent format so somebody
could do a meta-analysis of the entire uh thing um
yeah i mean sounds like a good project a big
project well i was going to put our data into
magic soon you know bits of it are there but not
all that stuff that we did back in the 90s yeah
i mean it depends also on the on the reasons
like what was the the research question behind
that like in our case because the for example the
net tectonic rotation analysis can restore it can
provide the initial dike orientation for example
i use that to reconstruct the the spreading system
in the neotecis by compiling multiple ovulites
from turkey greece cyprus and using that
i reconstructed also the subduction the geometry
of the subduction zone that was responsible
for the formation of those opulents now
that is a very specific question um right
and what we were interested in is what direction
was the magma flowing when it went in there
and yeah yeah so we had to do some kind of
rotation and we did it not the way you're doing it
but we did find that there were it
wasn't just vertical there was also this
yeah which can always happen yeah i mean indeed
flow directions could be another application of
metatonic rotation analysis of two two lines
i mean that's what we were after but you know
yeah there's just a lot of data on it exactly
it's good that the data are there and they're
not lost you know we can always find time and
and people to go further into the analysis
as far as the data are there they will be
there forever i guess and the samples yeah yeah
thank you well maybe i'll do
mine and then you can add yours
try to collect them all
okay thank you any other question maybe
we have time for one last question
tony yes go ahead again just the comment i think
i think marco's underplayed the importance of
this bigger study that he's mentioned about the
the sort of broader context of spreading in the
in the near tethys because um you know it's it's
easy to look at these what these single units and
and i think um you know all of that research
that lisa was referring to in cyprus over
over many um decades has been using this local
reference direction and it was it was marco's
insight to use actually the a northerly directive
reference direction that allowed him to work out
that the spreading axes aren't what you might
expect in tethys which you know you'd expect an
east-west trending ocean to have the east-west
training spreading axes but that's not the
case and and um and that that work was something
that solved problems about data that was sitting
around for years that no one really understood
how you ended up with these northeast trending
dike strikes in a in an east-west trending
ocean so it's just a comment really that
i think you know it's downplayed the extent
of that work goes far beyond cyprus which is
thank you yes thank you um oh we have another
question okay and then yeah so to come back to
uh lisa's remark about uh correcting the
flow or the magmatic flow in these dikes
we actually have a data set from dykes in
uh intruders and what we want to do is now
use the net tectonic rotation to correct back ams
patterns in these dikes to see what the flow is
so to do that full 3d restoration so
we'll see when we have time at hand to
get that done and see what kind of outcomes we
get and how much they differ from previous studies
good luck then sounds fun or a headache
yeah one of the things is uh how to to put
that net tectonic rotation in unisoft uh indeed
yeah okay thanks um i think it's time to
give another big round of applause to marco
thank you and yeah thank you very much for
presenting uh and um yeah if anybody else has
questions you know you can email marco or tony and
um yeah now we can uh okay share the latest slides
i fixed the date i got it wrong my
apologies thank you great presentation
so um yeah thanks again marco um our next
speaker will be in the sixth of april
journey janine from university of sao paulo on
the 4th of may gonna have sanya from jeff said
18 of my ween williams then we're going to stop
for egu and we are fully going to then move
to to eastern hemisphere timeslot and we
always welcome more speakers and i would like
uh to remind you that you can review re-watch and
spread these videos uh uh they're only on youtube
and you can cite them through ref and so thank
you very much all for coming and see you next time